<?xml version='1.0' standalone='no'?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
          "http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/mdp/docbkx412/docbookx.dtd">
<article>

<articleinfo>
  <title>MapServer Documentation Project Author Guide</title>

  <author>
     <firstname>Jamie</firstname>
     <surname>Smedsmo</surname>
     <affiliation>
        <orgname>University of Minnesota, Department of Forest Resources</orgname>
         <orgdiv>TerraSIP Project</orgdiv>
        <address>
            <email>jsmedsmo@gis.umn.edu</email>
        </address>
     </affiliation>
  </author>

  <abstract>
    <para>
    This document describes how to get started writing documents for the MapServer Documentation Project (MDP).
    </para>
    <para>Last Updated:  05-12-2001</para>
  </abstract>

</articleinfo>


<sect1 id='intro'>
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <sect2 id='purpose'>
    <title>Purpose and Scope of This Document</title>
    <para>
          This document is intended get you up-to-speed with how to write MapServer documentation.
          It will briefly discuss the preferred format for MDP documents as well as tools that can be 
          used to create and process MDP documents.  It will also give an overview of how to
          get started writing and submit what you have written.  
    </para>
    <para>
          Although a brief introduction to DocBook and XML are provided, this document is not 
          meant to provide a complete guide to creating DocBook XML documents.  Instead, it will
          direct you to other resources available on the web.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='mdp'>
    <title>The MDP</title>
    <para>
          The MapServer Documentation Project is a collaborative effort to provide free, 
          high-quality documentation for MapServer software.  The project is being coordinated
          by the TerraSIP project at the University of Minnesota Department of Forest Resources, 
          but the actual writing will be done by volunteers from the MapServer user community.
          MapServer users are invited to share their knowledge.
    </para>
    <para>
          The MDP will follow the Linux Documentation Project model with the goal of creating a
          set of task-specific HOWTO documents and a smaller set of Guides to be used as syntactic 
          references.  The MDP will accept documents written with the DocBook DTD, preferably 
          DocBook XML version 4.1.2.  If you choose to write documents using an SGML version of  
          the, please keep them xml compliant (<link linkend='xmlvsgml'>see XML vs. SGML</link>).
          Important documents may be accepted in other formats to be converted by a 
          volunteer from the MDP.
    </para>
    <para>
          Documentation will be made available through the MapServer web site at <ulink url='http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/doc.html'>http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/doc.html</ulink>

    </para>   
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='whydocbook'>
    <title>Why DocBook XML</title>
    <para>DocBook provides for more than just formatting. Free software 
          packages, such as Saxon and Xalan, transform DocBook XML into 
          other formats.  With these tools you can automatically build indexes, 
          table of contents, and links within or without the document.  
          Several editors are available that help you to write DocBook XML. 
          In the end, DocBook is more 
          concerned about defining the elements of a document than how they
          will be formatted in the end; stylesheets take care of that. This   
          distinction will help you write faster since you don't have to worry 
          about placement of paragraphs, font sizes, font types, and so on.
    </para>
  </sect2>

</sect1>


<sect1 id='tools'>
  <title>The Tools</title>
  
  <sect2 id='mdp_transform'>
    <title>The MDP DocBook XML to HTML Transformer</title>
     <para>
      A <ulink url='/cgi-bin/mdp_transform.cgi'>
      MDP Transformer</ulink> is available to preview DocBook XML documents
      without downloading any additional software.
      It uploads a local XML file, transforms it with the DocBook XSL stylesheets 
      and Saxon, and outputs an HTML version of the file.  If you use
      this tool you will not need the XSL stylesheets and XML processing tools
      listed below.  You will, however, need the DocBook DTD for your XML editor.
     </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id='docbookdtd'>
    <title>The DocBook DTD</title>
     <para>
      The DocBook XML DTD is available from <ulink url='http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.1.2/'>
      http://www.docbook.org/xml/4.1.2/</ulink>. 
      The DTD defines the tags and structure of a DocBook document.
     </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='xsl'>
    <title>XSL Stylesheets</title>
    <para>
         The latest version of the DocBook XSL stylesheets (currently 1.29) is available from
         <ulink url='http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xsl/'>http://nwalsh.com/docbook/xsl/</ulink>.
         The stylesheets specify the look and feel of your document when it is transformed to
         other formats.  There are stylesheets for several output formats including html and
         formatted output (used to create printable documents).  We will be using the basic 
         html/docbook.xsl for short documents and html/chunk.xsl for long documents. 
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='xmlproc'>
    <title>XML Processing Tools</title>
    <para>
         I have used two, free Java-based processing tools for XML transformation to HTML. 
         Saxon is available
         from <ulink url='http://users.iclway.co.uk/mhkay/saxon/'>
         http://users.iclway.co.uk/mhkay/saxon/</ulink>.  This seems to be quite a popular tool
         right now for use with DocBook XML with XSL stylesheets.  I was able to download a
         simplified version (Instant-Saxon) and get it running on a Windows-NT machine in about
         fifteen minutes.  One nice feature of Saxon is that it identifies errors in a document
         and outputs the error with the line number on which it was found.
    </para>
    <para>
         Xalan is part of the Apache XML project.  It is available from
         <ulink url='http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/'>
         http://xml.apache.org/xalan-j/</ulink>.  Xalan is also quite popular within the DocBook
         XML community.  It can be integrated with other Apache XML tools including one that
         produces PDF documents.  
     </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='editors'>
    <title>XML Editing Tools</title>
    <para>There are now quite a few tools available for editing XML ranging from WYSIWYG tool
          to extensions to traditional command-line editors.  <ulink 
          url='http://www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/~ht/xed.html'>XED</ulink> is a free GUI tool that reads
          your DTD and provides menus for element and attribute entries. 
          Emacs users should consider
          <ulink url='http://www.lysator.liu.se/projects/about_psgml.html'>psgmls</ulink>.
          <ulink url='http://nedit.org/'>Nedit</ulink> is a basic text editor with sgml/xml 
          syntax highlighting that runs on UNIX systems.
	  I have also heard good things about the <ulink url="http://www.xmlspy.com">XML Spy</ulink>;
	  a free 30-day evaluation version is available from the homepage.
       <itemizedlist> 
        <listitem><para>A list of <ulink url='http://www.linuxdoc.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/editing.html'>
        SGML editing,
        tools</ulink> from the Linux Documentation Project's Author Guide by Jorge Godoy and 
        David Merrill.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para><ulink url='http://www.ivritype.com/xml/'>A review</ulink> of some                              
                   editors from ivritype.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A more <ulink url='http://www.ltg.ed.ac.uk/~ht/xed.html'>complete list</ulink> of         
                   tools from xml.com.</para></listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
     </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='cvs'>
   <title>CVS</title>
   <para>MDP documents will be controlled through a Concurrent Version System (CVS).  There are
         several advantages to using a CVS: 
    <orderedlist> 
     <listitem><para>CVS will keep an off-site backup of your documents. This also 
               provides a way to exchange a document under development by several authors.</para></listitem>           
     <listitem><para>CVS can integrate changes from several authors working on a 
              document at the same time.</para></listitem> 
     <listitem><para>CVS keeps a log of what changes have been made to a document 
              and allows retrieval of old versions.</para></listitem> 
    </orderedlist>  
    If you are new to CVS, there are some good references available through <ulink url='http://www.cvshome.org/'>the CVS home page</ulink>.</para>

   <para>For access to the MDP CVS, contact the documentation coordinator at 
        <email>mdp@lists.gis.umn.edu</email>.</para>
  
  </sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1 id='writing'>
  <title>Writing a Document</title>
  
  <sect2 id='template'>
    <title>The MDP XML template</title>
    <para>
      The MDP HOWTO Template in <ulink url="mdp-howto-template.html">HTML</ulink> and DocBook 
      <ulink url="mdp-howto-template.xml">XML</ulink> gives you a document skeleton
      (to download the XML file right click on the link and select "Save Link As...").
    </para>
  </sect2>
  
  <sect2 id='topic'>
    <title>Choosing a Topic</title>
    <para>
      You may choose any topic for which documentation is needed or choose a topic from the 
      <ulink url='http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/mdp/current_projects.html'>current projects list</ulink>.  The idea is to focus on HOWTOs, so
      choose a clearly-defined topic that is not too narrow and not to broad.  
      Also make sure your topic is undocumented.
      When you have chosen a topic, let the documentation coordinator 
      <email>mdp@lists.gis.umn.edu</email> know what you are working on.  
      Maintaining a current list of what is being written will prevent duplication of effort.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='DocBook Tags'>
    <title>DocBook Tags</title>

    <para>
    For complete documentation "DocBook: The Definitive Guide," by Norm Walsh and Leonard Muellner is
    available online from <ulink url='http://www.docbook.org/'>http://www.docbook.org/</ulink>.
    </para>

    <para>
    There is a useful section in the Linux Documentation Project Author Guide that discusses
    the most commonly used DocBook markup tags and compatibility between SGML and XML. It
    can be used as a <ulink url='http://www.linuxdoc.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/writing-docbook.html'>
    abbreviated DocBook reference</ulink>.  Note there is a typo in the second paragraph where
    is recommends keeping you elements in <emphasis>upper case</emphasis> for compatibility with XML.  
    Element and attribute tags should actually be in <emphasis>lower case</emphasis>.
    </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='xmlvsgml'>
    <title>XML versus SGML</title>
    <para>
    If you are writing with a DocBook SGML DTD it is not difficult to keep the document
    XML compliant.  Some editors, such as psgmls+emacs, do this automatically.  There are a
    few points to keep in mind (as outlined in <ulink url='http://www.docbook.org/'>
    DocBook: The Definitive Guide</ulink>).
     <itemizedlist>
      <listitem><para>All elements, attributes, and entity names must be typed in lowercase.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Attribute values must be enclosed in quotes; you may use single
                      or double quotes, but not curly quotes.</para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Do not use empty elements or any markup minimization and do not omit end tags.
                </para></listitem>
      <listitem><para>Comments are not allowed inside markup declarations.</para></listitem>
     </itemizedlist>
    </para>
  
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='submit'>
   <title>Submitting a Document</title>
    <para>
     To submit your new document just add it to the CVS.  The document will be edited
     to ensure a certain amount of uniformity between documents, and an edited
     version will be posted for your review.  When you have given the OK, the
     new document will be transformed to HTML and added to the MapServer documentation
     page.
    </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='maillists'>
    <title>Mailing Lists</title>
     <para>
     Several MapServer mailing list are available.  Issues such as documentation format
     and documentation needed are discussed on the MapServer Docs list.  To subscribe,
     send an email message to <email>majordomo@lists.gis.umn.edu</email> containing two
     lines:
      <programlisting>
         subscribe mapserver-docs
         END 
      </programlisting>
     A confirmation message will be sent to you to which you must respond before you will
     actually be added to the list.
     </para>
     <para>
     To unsubscribe, send a message to <email>majordomo@lists.gis.umn.edu
     </email> containing two lines:
      <programlisting>
         unsubscribe mapserver-docs
         END 
      </programlisting>
     </para>
     <para>
      The mapserver-users listserv was created as a means for MapServer users and
      developers to exchange application ideas, discuss potential software 
      improvements, and ask questions.
      A <ulink url='http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/cgi-bin/wilma/mapserver-users'>
      searchable archive</ulink> of the mapserver-users list is available.
     </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='writingrefs'>
    <title>Other Writing References</title>
    <para>
     For tips on writing, check out the <ulink url='http://www.linuxdoc.org/LDP/LDP-Author-Guide/styleguide.html'>
    Style Guide</ulink> from the Linux Documentation Project's Author Guide.
    </para> 
  </sect2>

</sect1>

<!-- Translation -->
<sect1 id='docinfo'> 
  <title>Translating to Other Languages</title>
  <para>Translation of MapServer Documentation to other languages is encouraged.  The translated documents will be stored in
        the CVS in the same branch as other documents with an extension the indicate which language
        it is in.  The two-letter extension is determined by the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/WAI/ER/IG/ert/iso639.htm">
        ISO-639 standard</ulink>.  For example, a spanish translation of getstarted-howto.xml will be stored
        as get-started-howto_es.xml.
  </para>

  <para>The translator will be specified in the document with the "othercredit" tag within the "articleinfo" 
  as shown in the example below:

  <programlisting>
  <![CDATA[
  <othercredit>
     <contrib>Translation:</contrib>
     <firstname>Jamie</firstname>
     <surname>Smedsmo</surname>
     <affiliation>
        <orgname>University of Minnesota</orgname>
         <orgdiv>TerraSIP Project</orgdiv>
        <address>
            <email>jsmedsmo@gis.umn.edu</email>
        </address>
     </affiliation>
  </othercredit>
  ]]>
  </programlisting>

  </para>

</sect1>



<sect1 id='docinfo'> 
  <title>About This Document</title>

  <sect2 id='copyright'>
   <title>Copyright Information</title>
   
   <para>
   Copyright (c) 1996-2000 Regents of the University of Minnesota.
   <ulink url='http://mapserver.gis.umn.edu/license.html'>License and Credits</ulink>.
   </para>
  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='disclaimer'>
   <title>Disclaimer</title>

   <para>
    No liability for the contents of this document can be accepted.
    Use the concepts, examples and other content at your own risk.
    As this is a new edition of this document, there may be errors
    and inaccuracies that may be damaging to your system.
    Although this is highly unlikely, the author(s) do not take any 
    responsibility for that:  proceed with caution.
   </para>

  </sect2>

  <sect2 id='credits'>
   <title>Acknowledgments</title>
   <para>
    This document was heavily influenced by the LDP Author Guide by Mark
    Komarinski, Jorge Godoy, and David Merrill.
   </para>
  </sect2>

<!-- Section2: feedback -->

  <sect2 id='feedback'>
   <title>Feedback</title>
   <para>
    Send any comments or suggestions to the document author(s).
   </para>
   </sect2>

 </sect1>

</article>
